Mss.B.P63 Mss.B.P63
American Philosophical Society
Zebulon Montgomery Pike biographical materials, 1780-1956
Mss.B.P63
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
51 items, photostats.
Zebulon Montgomery Pike (1779-1813) was an explorer and soldier, most often remembered two exploratory trips to the newly acquired Louisiana territory. The first of these trips was to the source of the Mississippi River in 1805; the second was to explore the headwaters of the Arkansas and Red Rivers in 1806. Because General James Wilkinson was responsible for organizing Pike’s two expeditions, when the conspiracy charges again Aaron Burr implicated Wilkinson, suspicion was, for a short time, also focused on Pike. Pike worked his way up the ranks of the United States Army, becoming a brigadier-general during the War of 1812. He was killed in the Battle of York in Upper Canada (now Toronto) in 1813.
Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
Box 1
Scope and Contents note
This collection includes transcripts and photostats of letters, maps, and some original manuscripts collected by W. Eugene Hollon for his biography of Pike, The Lost Pathfinder (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1949). Correspondents include John C. Calhoun, William Clark, Richard Rush, John Sibley, and James Wilkinson. Subjects covered include military authority, escaped slaves, Pike’s expeditions, Texas, Aaron Burr and James Wilkinson. Copies of materials from the National Archives, the Chicago Historical Society, and the Missouri Historical Society.
Bibliography
Hollon, William Eugene, "The Lost Pathfinder, Zebulon Montgomery Pike" (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, c1949).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by W. Eugene Hollon, 1950; accessioned, 1958 (1958 1627ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Zebulon Montgomery Pike (1779-1813) was an explorer and soldier, most often remembered two exploratory trips to the newly acquired Louisiana territory. The first of these trips was to the source of the Mississippi River in 1805; the second was to explore the headwaters of the Arkansas and Red Rivers in 1806. Because General James Wilkinson was responsible for organizing Pike’s two expeditions, when the conspiracy charges again Aaron Burr implicated Wilkinson, suspicion was, for a short time, also focused on Pike. Pike worked his way up the ranks of the United States Army, becoming a brigadier-general during the War of 1812. He was killed in the Battle of York in Upper Canada (now Toronto) in 1813.
Zebulon Montgomery Pike was born in Lamberton (now part of Trenton), New Jersey in 1779. His father was also named Zebulon Montgomery and his mother was Isabella Brown. His father served in the Revolutionary Army under Washington and remained in the Army after the Revolution, eventually reaching the rank of Major. Pike entered the Army early, joining his father’s company as a cadet. At the age of twenty he was commissioned a first lieutenant.
In 1805 Pike was chosen by General James Wilkinson to head a company of twenty men to explore the source of the Mississippi River. After the onset of winter, Pike reached what he mistakenly declared the source of the river. In 1806 he was chosen to lead a longer expedition to the headwaters of the Arkansas and Red Rivers. Part of his mission was to reconnoiter the Spanish settlements in New Mexico. After Pike crossed the Sangre de Cristo Mountains in 1807, Spanish authorities arrested him for crossing their border. Pike acquiesced freely, welcoming the chance to see the territory of Santa Fe and Chihuahua, where he was questioned by the commandante general.
After his return to the United States, Pike found himself under suspicion by some of being part of the Wilkinson-Burr conspiracy to acquire land in the Southwest. Henry Dearborn, the Secretary of State, cleared Pike of all charges related the conspiracy, and Pike continued military duty. He was commissioned major in 1808 and colonel in 1812. When the second war with Great Britain started in 1812, Pike was made brigadier-general. He led the attack on York (now Toronto), Canada in 1813. While the campaign was successful, Pike was killed when a powder magazine exploded. Pike is best remembered for his expeditions to the Southwest, for which his journals have been published in several additions. Several counties are named for him in various states, and Pikes Peak, a mountain in the Front Range of the Rocky Mountains, is named in his honor.
Early American History Note
The Zebulon Montgomery Pike Biographical Material Collection contains research data on Pike that Eugene Hollon compiled for his biography of Pike. There are some photocopies and transcriptions of correspondence and other primary sources.
Calhoun, John C., (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Clark, William, 1770-1838; Hollon, W. Eugene, (William Eugene), 1913-; Rush, Richard; Sibley, John, 1757-1837; Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825; Exploration.; Explorers.; General Correspondence; Maps.; Research Records and Reports; Travel
- Papers and material, 1780-1956
  Scope and Contents note
  collected by W. Eugene Hollan for his biography of Pike, The Lost Pathfinder. D.and printed items. 51 items (typed, original and photostats), 5 photographs, and 19 leaves of printed materials, including 2 maps. Various sizes. See Film 890 for microfilms which came with this collection. Presented by Hollan, grantee, Jan. 1950,and entered in APS Donation Book, p.229,Jan.23,1950. Table of contents.
  - Letter to Anthony Wayne, July 21, 1780; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Photostat of A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Military information.
  - Letter to William Knox, Philadelphia, Aug. 23, 1792; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Trenton, Photostat of A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Requests material for soldiers.
  - Letter to John Mells, Greensville, Dec. 18, 1793; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Greensville, Photostat of L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning the arrest for court martial of an officer.
  - Military documents signed by Z.M. Pike and Zeb[ulo]n Pike, 1795-1812; United States. Army
    Photostats of D. 9 leaves. Various sizes. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Letter to [Zebulon Montgomery] Pike, Sept. 2, 1796; Wayne, Anthony, 1745-1796
    Detroit, Photostat of L. 1p.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Military orders.
  - Letter to Andrew Ellicott, Dec. 31, 1796; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Massac, Photostat of L.S. 1p.and add. (see Z.M.Pike. Papers...) Concerning "his embassy" and hope for its success.
  - Receipt to John Wilkins, for military funds, May 9, 1800; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Photostat of D.S. 1p.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Letter to D[avi]d Henley, June 3, 1800; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    For Pickering, Photostat of A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Z.M.Pike. Papers...) Concerning some negroes who have escaped from slavery from the Indians.
  - Letter to William Linnard, Philadelphia, July 19, 1805; 11x8-1/2; Mulford, Clarence
    St. Louis, Typed L. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Business. Expense of Pike's expedition to the source of the Mississippi.
  - Diary, 1806; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    ca. Photostats of A.D. 5p.of which 3 are maps and 2 are meteorological data. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Letter to [Henry] Dearborn, May 18, 1807; 11x8-1/2; Clark, William, 1770-1838
    St. Louis, Typed L. 5p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning the Indian of the mid-West. Refers to Pike. Enc.originally in letter; J.Sibley to S.H.Sibley; June 30, 1807.
  - Letter to Samuel H. Sibley, June 30, 1807; 11x8-1/2; Sibley, John, 1757-1837
    Natchitoches, Typed L. 4p. Copy. Enc. ( see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Business. Concerning Burr and Wilkinson. Concerning Burr and Wilkinson. Concerning Pikes expedition. Concerning the Indians. For enc., see: W.Clark to H.Dearborn; May 18, 1807.
  - Order book, Aug. 22, 1808 - May 3, 1810; 11x8-1/2; Fort Bellefontaine, Missouri
    Typed D. 2p. Extracts. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Z.M.Pike.
  - Receipt for military stores received, Aug. 30, 1809; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    New Orleans; Photostat of D.S. 2p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Garrison orders, July 1, 1811; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    Baton Rouge, Photostat of A.D. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Garrison orders, 1811; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    Photostat of D.S.: Z.M. Pike, et al. 6p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Letter to the Governor of Texas, Manuel de Salcedo, Feb. 20, 1812; Montero, Bernardino
    Photostat of L.S. 2p. In Spanish. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Pike's expedition to wipe out the bandits.
  - Letter to Bernard[i]no Montero, Feb. 26, 1812; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    Nachitoches, Photostat of L. 2p. Copy. In Spanish (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Printed in part: Hollon. The Lost Pathfinder; 195.
  - Letter to Manuel de Salcedo, March 1, 1812; Montero, Bernardino
    Photostat of L.S. 2p. In Spanish. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Pike and his wish to scour the robbers.
  - Letter to James Wilkinson, Washington, March 31, 1812; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    Baton Rouge, Photostat of D.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Introduces Lt. King.
  - Letter to the Governor of Texas, Manuel de Salcedo, April 1, 1812; Montero, Bernardino
    Nacogdoches, Photostat of L.S. 1p.,end. In Spanish. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Forwards letters by Z.M. Pike, et al.
  - Letter to the Governor of Texas, Manuel de Salcedo, April 1, 1812; Montero, Bernardino
    Photostat of L.S. 2p. In Spanish. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Copies a letter from Pike concerning cooperation in getting rid of bandits.
  - Letter to Captain Montero, March 21, 1812; Overton, Walter Hampden, 1788-1845
    Nachitoches, Photostat of L.S. 2p. In Spanish. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning the activities of Pike.
  - Letter to James Wilkinson, Washington, March 31, 1812; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
  - Letter to the Governor of Texas [Manuel de Salcedo], May 12, 1812; Salcedo y Salcedo, Nemesio, 1754-1814?
    Photostat of L.S. 1p. In Spanish. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Pike.
  - Letter to Major Stoddard, April 2, 1812; 11x8-1/2; Sibley, John, 1757-1837
    Natchitoches, Typed L. 4p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Mexico, Pike, the Indians, and internal affairs of the U.S. Refers to mineralogy. Printed in part: Hollon. The Lost Pathfinder, 196.
  - Statement of need of Zebulon Pike, Sept. 5, 1818; 11x8-1/2; Parke, Benjamin, 1777-1835
    Typed D. 2p. Certified by Sam. Crane. (see Z.M.Pike. Papers...)
  - Oath, declaration of need, and schedule of property, June 12, 1823; 10-1/2x8; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Typed D. 3p. Certified: James Dill. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Letter to J[ohn] C. Calhoun, Washington, April, 1824; 10-1/2x8; Dill, James, 1772-1838
    Lawrenceburg, Ind., Typed L. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Pike's promise of full pay from Jefferson, and his need for funds.
  - Concerning monies paid to Zebulon Pike from the Revolutionary list, 1824; 6x8-1/2; U.S.
    Typed D. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - An act granting pensions to James Barker and Zebulon Pike, March 3, 1825; 10-1/2x8; United States
    Washington, Typed D. 1p. Approved: James Monroe. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) ---Typed copy. 5x8-1/2.
  - Letter to Richard Rush, July 1, 1828; 10-1/2x8; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Lawrenceburg, Ind., Typed L. 2p.,witnessed by James Dill and John Fist. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Forwards documents for relief.
  - Zebulon M[ontgomery] Pike. A Hero of the War of 1812, Jan. 8, 1906; 11x8-1/2; The Daily Democrat, Doylestown, Penna.
    Typed D. 4p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Concerning Clara Brown Pike, wife of Zebulon Montgomery Pike, Oct. 20, 1927; 14x8-1/2; The Lawrenceburg Press, Lawrenceburg, Ind.
    D. 2p. Mimeographed. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Survey of Federal Archives in Louisiana, Book II, (Part 2) Greensburg Land Claims British West Florida, 1940; 11x8-1/2; Work projects administration. Louisiana
    Typed D. 6p. Extracts. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning a land claim referring to Z.M. Pike.
  - Concerning Pike's journal of his trip up the Mississippi, 1805-1806, Sept. 16, 1946; 11x8-1/2; May, T. R.
    Locust Valley, Typed D. 6p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Letter to [W. Eugene] Hollon, Oct. 16, 1946; 11x8-1/2; Pike Family Association
    A.D.S.: Lilian Pike Packard. 9 leaves. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Z.M. Pike.
  - Map of Fort Bellefontaine, 1946; 1 map, 21.6 x 35.4 cm; Mills, Edwin
    Fort Bellefontaine was the first United States Army post west of the Mississippi River. It was established by General James Wilkinson in 1804.
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 39 (1).
  - Letter to [W. Eu]gene Hollon, Norman, Oklahoma, Feb. 13, 1947; 11x8-1/2; Goldmann, Sidney, 1903-
    Trenton, Typed D.S. 2p.,end. (see Z.M.Pike. Papers...) Concerning Z.M.Pike's ancestors in New Jersey.
  - Letter to [W. Eu]gene Hollon, Norman, Oklahoma, Feb. 25, 1947; 10-1/2x7; Evans, David R.
    Somerville, N.J., Typed L.S. 2p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning the location of Zebulon Pike's birth.
  - Letter to W. E[ugene] Hollon, Norman, Oklahoma, May 22, 1947; 11x8-1/2; Missouri Historical Society
    St. Louis, Typed L.S.: Brenda R. Gieseker, Librarian 1p.,end. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Concerning Z.M.Pike material in the manuscript collection.
  - Pike's expedition up the Osage, 1806, April 29, 1956; 11x8-1/2; Mills, Edwin W.
    Typed D.S. 26p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - Statement concerning Zebulon Pike's request for relief, Undated; 10-1/2x8; Dill, James, 1772-1838
    Lawrenceburg, Ind., [ca.1824]. Typed D. 2p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - List of issues of the Weekly Chronicle of Natchez, Undated; 11x8-1/2; Hollon, W. Eugene (William Eugene), 1913-
    Miss., concerning Z.M.Pike. Typed D. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)
  - List of Letters from W. C. C. Claiborne's letterbooks in which Zebulon M. Pike is mentioned, Undated; 11x8-1/2; Hollon, W. Eugene (William Eugene), 1913-
    Typed D. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. papers...)
  - List of children of Zebulon and Isabel Brown Pike, Undated; Pike, Zebulon, 1751-1834
    Photostat of D. 1p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...) Lists Z.M. Pike among them.
  - Genealogical material, Undated; 11x8-1/2; Pike, Zebulon Montgomery, 1779-1813
    D. 6p. (see Z.M. Pike. Papers...)